Well, I'm delighted to welcome you to day three of our eight week journey together.
8주간의 여정 중 3일째에 오신 걸 환영해요
And today we're going to be looking at Frontier Models.
오늘은 개척 시대 모델을 볼 거예요
The idea that the goal of today is to get deep into these different models so that you can get a true
오늘 우리가 할 일은 이 다양한 모델을 깊이 파고들어 어떤 모델이 강하고 어떤 모델이
intuition for where are they strong, where are they weak, what are the differences between them?
약하며 어떤 차이가 있는지 알아내는 거예요.
And so that's what I want you to keep in mind throughout today's material, learning about the differences
오늘 강의에서 명심해야 할 점은 두 모델의 차이점을 파악하고 상업적으로
between them and thinking about how you would apply them commercially to your business or to future
어떻게 사업을 진행할지 향후 프로젝트에 어떻게 적용할지 생각해 보세요
projects, and understanding when you would pick which model.
언제 어떤 모델을 선택할지도요
Let's get to it.
Get it, get it 해 보죠
So we're going to be talking about six different models today from six different companies, starting
오늘은 6개의 다른 모델에 대해 이야기해 볼 텐데요 6개의 다른
of course, with OpenAI's models.
회사의 모델로 시작해 보죠
OpenAI needs no introduction really.
오픈아이는 소개가 필요 없죠
GPT is the most famous model.
GPT가 가장 유명한 모델이죠
And we'll also, of course look at 0101 preview.
0101 프리뷰도 물론 보고요
The the newest of their models and ChatGPT is their user interface, the screens where you can interact
챗GPT의 최신 모델은 사용자 인터페이스입니다 인터페이스를 통해 상호 작용을 할
with it.
수 있죠
We'll also look at the models from anthropic.
인스로픽 모델도 살펴볼 거예요
Anthropic is OpenAI's top competitor, based in San Francisco as well, and founded by some people that
안트로픽은 샌프란시스코에 있는 오픈AI의 경쟁 업체예요 오픈아이를 떠난 사람들이
left OpenAI, and their model is called Claude and Claude.
설립했죠 그들의 모델은 클로드와 클로드예요
In fact, you may know, comes in sort of three powers.
사실, 세 가지 힘이 있어요
The smallest one is called haiku.
가장 작은 건 하이쿠예요
Claude haiku, and then the sonnet.
클로드 하이쿠와 소네트예요
And then there's opus.
오퍼스가 있네요
But actually, because sonnet has had much more recent versions, the latest version of sonnet is stronger
하지만 소네트는 훨씬 더 최근에 만들어진 작품들이기 때문에 최신 버전의 소네트가
than the bigger, more expensive opus, as we'll see.
더 크고 비싼 작품들보다 더 강해요
That will make more sense later.
나중에 더 이해가 될 거예요
But Claude Claude 3.5 sonnet is the strongest of Claude's models.
클로드 3세예요 클로드의 작품 중 가장 강렬한 소네트 5편이 있죠
Google has Google Gemini, probably latest to the party, and most of us know Gemini most well because
구글에 제미니 제미니가 있어요 아마 가장 최근일 거예요 대부분 제미니 제미니를 잘 알죠 요즘
nowadays when we do a Google search, very often we see Gemini's responses.
구글 검색을 하면 제미니 제미니의 반응이 나오거든요
Gemini is, of course, the next generation of what was originally called Bard from Google.
제미니는 차세대 게임으로 구글에서 바르드로 불렸죠
Cohere is one that you may have heard less about.
코어라는 이름은 less로 들어봤을 거예요
It's a Canadian AI company, and their model is most well known for being using using a technique called
캐나다 인공지능 회사로 래그라는 기술을 이용해 전문성을 확보하는
Rag to make sure that it has expertise.
것으로 유명하죠
So we will see that.
곧 알게 되겠죠
And then we know the llama model from meta.
그리고 메타에서 라마를 알게 되었죠
We've used it ourselves through llama.
우리도 라마를 통해 사용했어요
This is an open source model, and you may not know that the meta actually also has a website, meta
이건 오픈 소스 모델입니다 여러분은 잘 모르시겠지만 메타에는 llama
AI, that lets you interact with the llama model.
모델과 상호 작용을 하는 웹사이트 메타 인공지능도 있어요
And we will have a look at that.
그걸 살펴볼 거예요
And then perplexity is a bit different, because perplexity is actually a search engine powered by AI,
여기서 당혹감은 조금 다릅니다 당혹감은 사실 LM으로 작동하는 인공지능으로 작동하는 검색 엔진으로
powered by Llms, and it can use some of the other models that we'll talk about.
우리가 얘기할 다른 모델도 사용할 수 있죠
But they do also have their own model too, so it's a slightly different beast, but we'll be looking
하지만 자체 모델도 있어요 약간 다른 괴물이죠 하지만 당혹스럽기도
at perplexity as well.
할 거예요
So overall, these llms are astonishing in what they are capable of.
전반적으로 llms의 능력은 정말 놀라워요
They are really very effective indeed at taking a detailed question, a nuanced question, and providing
상세하고 미묘한 질문을 분석하고 충분한 조사를 거친 후 구조적으로
a structured summary that appears well researched.
요약하는 데 매우 효과적이죠
It often has a sort of introduction and a summary, and this is one of the ways that I use it all the
종종 소개와 요약이 있어요 제가 늘 사용하는 방법 중
time.
하나죠
and I find that across the board, these llms are shocking in how good they are at this.
전반적으로 llm의 성능이 놀라울 정도로 뛰어나요
It's something that a couple of years ago, none of us would have imagined that we could get this far
몇 년 전만 해도 이렇게 빨리 완성할 줄은 아무도 몰랐어요 Get
this quickly.
up
There are also really good, and I imagine that many of you do this a lot yourselves, and I do it if
또 좋은 것도 있어요. 많은 분들이 해보셨을 것 같은데, 저도 총알을
you put in a few bullets, just a few notes on something and say, hey, can you turn this into an email
몇 개 넣고, 몇 가지 메모만 넣고, 이것들을 이메일이나
or can you turn this into a slide?
슬라이드로 바꿀 수 있나요?
They are really good at fleshing it out and building, say, a blog post, and they're very good at
구체화하는 데 능숙하고 블로그 post를 만들거나 반복하는 데 능숙하죠
So they'll do something and are like some of it I won't like others.
어떤 걸 하면 어떤 건 좋아하고 어떤 건 싫어하죠
And you can give feedback and keep going backwards and forwards.
피드백을 주고 계속 진행할 수 있어요
And it's a really effective way of working.
아주 효과적인 작업 방식이죠
It's the kind of copilot construct that is so, so, so effective.
부조종사 구조가 정말 효과적이에요
And then coding, of course.
물론 코딩도 있고요
And perhaps this for many of us is is the thing that is most staggering is how very good the llms are
그리고 아마도 많은 사람들에게 가장 놀라운 것은 llms가 코드를 작성하고 디버깅을 하고 문제를
at writing code and debugging problems and solving them.
해결하는 데에 아주 뛰어나다는 것일 거예요
It's something which is really remarkable.
정말 놀라운 일이죠
I've had experiences myself when I've been working on something that's very complex, and it's something
저도 아주 복잡한 걸 작업하면서 그런 경험을 했어요 제가
that I believe I have deep subject matter expertise in, and I've got a fairly intricate error, and
심오한 주제 분야의 전문성을 갖고 있다고 믿는 거죠 꽤 복잡한 오류가 있었어요
I put the details and the stack trace in into Claude, say, and I get back not only a very precise
클로드에 상세 정보와 스택 트레이스를 넣으면 무엇이 잘못됐는지에 대한 아주 정확한 설명만 갖고 오는
explanation of what's going wrong, but also the code that will fix it appearing as an artifact on the
게 아니라 오른쪽에 아티팩트로 보이는 그걸 고칠 코드도 갖고 오죠
And it's it's it's amazing.
정말 놀라워요
And in fact, these are often things which I if I try and paste them, if I look for it in Stack Overflow,
사실 이런 건 종종∙∙∙ 붙여넣기를 하려고 하면 스택 오버플로에서
there's no answer there.
찾아도 답이 없어요
Somehow it's it's able to look beyond just, just a regurgitating Stack Overflow answers.
역류하는 스택 오버플로의 답을 넘어설 수 있어요
And it seems to have real insight into what's going on.
무슨 일이 일어나는지 제대로 통찰하는 것 같아요
And I suppose that's why it's not surprising, really, that Stack Overflow has seen a big falloff in
그래서 스택 오버플로에서 트래픽이 크게 하락한 게 놀랍지 않은 것
its traffic.
같아요
You can see that something started to happen in a big way after Q4 2022, which is when ChatGPT was
2022년 Q4 이후부터 큰 변화가 일어났습니다 챗GPT가 출시된 시기죠
So, you know, it's obviously changed the paradigm of how uh, how we how technology people work with
그래서 확실히 패러다임을 바꿨어요 우리 문제를 조사하는 기술에 대한
with researching our problems.
패러다임요
It's very effective.
아주 효과적이죠
And I encourage you, if you get stuck with some of the things we work on to give Claude or OpenAI GPT
여러분도 저희가 하는 것 중에 막히는 게 있다면 클로드나 오픈라이 GPT에 도전해
a shot.
보세요
So what about where are they weak?
그럼 어디가 약점일까요?
What are the things that they struggle with?
그들이 힘들어하는 건 무엇일까요?
Where does humanity still have a chance in all of this?
인류에게 아직 기회가 있을까요?
Well, so first of all, they tend to not be as strong with specialized subject matter if it's something
우선, 상세한 지식이 필요한 특수한 대상에는 그리 강한
that requires detailed knowledge.
힘이 없어요
Most llms are not yet at PhD level.
대부분의 llm은 아직 박사 단계가 아니에요
Now, I had to put the word most in there because literally just just just a few weeks ago for me in
거의 모든 단어를 써야 했어요 왜냐하면 몇 주 전만 해도 10월에 클로드 최신 버전이
October, uh, Claude, the newest version of Claude came out, uh, the latest Claude 3.5 sonnet,
나왔거든요 최신 클로드 3요 Put 5개의 소네트 수학, 물리,
uh, and it has surpassed PhD level in maths, physics, chemistry.
화학에서 박사 수준을 넘어섰어요
Uh, and so this is something where very quickly we're seeing these models achieving PhD level.
이 모델들이 순식간에 박사 수준을 달성하는 걸 볼 수 있었죠
So far just Claude.
아직까진 클로드뿐이에요
But the others I'm sure are not far behind, but those are in those specific sciences and in a particular
다른 사람들도 마찬가지겠지만 그들은 특정 과학 분야에 있고 사업 분야
domain, like a business domain, they still won't have the specialist knowledge of an expert in that
같은 특정 영역에 있어서 그 분야의 전문가가 가진 전문 지식이 없어요
And secondly, recent events.
둘째, 최근 사건들요
So the models have been trained up until a knowledge cutoff, which is for GPT.
모델들은 GPT를 위한 지식 제한 시간까지 훈련받아요
October of last year.
작년 10월요
And so they won't be able to answer questions on information that has come since then.
그 이후에 나온 질문에 대답할 수 없게 되죠
And then they have some strange blind spots.
그리고 이상한 사각지대도 있어요
There are some questions which they will just get wrong.
Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it! 어떤 질문들은 그냥 틀릴 수도 있어요
And when they get them wrong, one of the things that's quite concerning is that they do tend to be
그리고 틀렸을 때 걱정되는 점은 get it 부문은 자신의 반응에
confident in their responses.
확신이 있다는 거죠
They often don't volunteer the fact that they're uncertain.
불확실하다는 사실을 자발적으로 말하지 않죠
They just state an answer with the same level of conviction as with something where they do get the
정답을 맞히는 것과 같은 수준의 확신에 찬 답변을 할 뿐이죠. Get up! Get
answer right.
up!
And that that is something which of course causes concern when you see models hallucinate or come up
그건 당연히 우려를 낳죠 환각을 보거나 새로운 정보를 떠올릴 때요 본인은 모르고
with with new information which it doesn't know and do so with confidence.
자신 있게 그렇게 하는 거죠
And we'll see some examples of that and talk about what are the reasons behind those blind spots.
몇 가지 예제를 보고 그런 맹점 뒤에 있는 이유를 말씀드리죠